<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An impartial and brief description of the plaza, or sumptuous market-place of Madrid, and the bull-baiting there together with the history of the famous and much admired Placidus : as also a large scheme : being the liverly representation of the Order of Ornament of this solemnity / by James Salgado ...</title>
            <author>Salgado, James, fl. 1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60221</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S377</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R16238</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12393686</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12393686</idno>
            <idno type="VID">61065</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60221)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 61065)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 225:20)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An impartial and brief description of the plaza, or sumptuous market-place of Madrid, and the bull-baiting there together with the history of the famous and much admired Placidus : as also a large scheme : being the liverly representation of the Order of Ornament of this solemnity / by James Salgado ...</title>
                  <author>Salgado, James, fl. 1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 46 [i.e. 38] p., [1] folded leaf of plates : ill., port.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Francis Clark for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bullfights --  Spain --  Madrid.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:61065:1"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>portrait of King Charles II</figDesc>
                  <head>CAROLUS II DEI GRATIA ANGLIAE SCOTIAE FRANCIAE ET HIBERNIA REX ETC.</head>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:61065:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>An Impartial and Brief DESCRIPTION OF THE PLAZA, Or Sumptuous <hi>Market-Place</hi> OF MADRID, AND THE Bull-Baiting THERE: Together with the Hiſtory of the Famous and much Admired <hi>Placidus.</hi> As alſo a large Scheme, being the Lively Repreſentation of the Order and Ornament of this Solemnity.</p>
            <p>By <hi>James Salgado</hi> a Spaniard.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Francis Clark</hi> for the Author, <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:61065:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:61065:2"/>
            <head>TO THE MOST SERENE and MIGHTY CHARLES II.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>By the Grace of God of</hi> Great Brittain, France <hi>and</hi> Ireland <hi>King, Defender of the Faith,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe Your Moſt Excellent Majeſty,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Royal Name was prefixed to this other Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nual of mine the laſt year, but I had not the Confidence to preſent Your Sacred Majeſty with the ſame: It was not that I judged the Subject matter altogether deſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable,
<pb facs="tcp:61065:3"/>and unworthy of Acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; but becauſe my Timerous and Baſhful Diſpoſition induced me to believe that it was every way ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, to be Honoured with the Name of ſuch an Ineſtimable and Noble Patron: But yet for all that, my Pinching want has, now at length, prevail'd with me to ſhake off theſe Thoughts; in regard that ſo great an Honour, attended with ſomthing elſe (Your Majeſty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives my meaning) would, beyond all peradventure, contribute the more to my preſent Straitned condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore I Proſtrate my Self and Labours at Your Royal Feet; looking upon it as my greateſt Happineſs, if Your Majeſty may be pleaſed to ſpend ſome few Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nutes
<pb facs="tcp:61065:3"/>for a Recreation, in the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſal of this ſhort Deſcription of the <hi>Bull-Baiting</hi> at <hi>Madrid:</hi> But if good Fortune deny me this Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, I muſt Patiently ſhare in the Lot of my Country-men, who now a-days are generally Unfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate. However, Your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties long Life, Proſperous Reign, and Eternal Happineſs, ſhall in all Circumſtances, be the moſt Ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Majeſties moſt Devoted Supplicant,</hi> James Salgado <hi>a</hi> Spaniard.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:61065:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Have taken a view of <hi>Spain, France, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and the <hi>United Netherlands,</hi> but I muſt confeſs, I did never ſee (except here in <hi>England</hi>) ſuch a crowd of <hi>Authors, Printers, Book-binders, Stationers, Gazetts, Obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, Pacquets, Mercuries, Intelligences,</hi> and <hi>Bills</hi> of <hi>Chyrurgions,</hi> calling themſelves <hi>Doctors</hi> forſooth: Whileas, in very deed, they ought to be ſtiled <hi>Mountebanks.</hi> In a word, I don't remember to have ſeen a People ſo much buſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d with, and Fond upon No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velties. While therefore I ſtood amaz'd, behold pinching Want, and ſimple Baſhful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs (by way of a Dialogue) made their ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſs unto me; the former in theſe following words. I ſee you are a Stranger, and ought
<pb facs="tcp:61065:4"/>to be encouraged by, and ſheltered under the Protection of the Generous <hi>Engliſh</hi> Nation: For that cauſe, I judge it your near concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to come with a full hand, if you look for any gracious acceptance. On the other ſide Shame replyed, Mr. <hi>Salgado</hi> believe my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſembled Simplicity; The <hi>Engliſh</hi> are moſt Ingenuous, and of a Pregnant Wit: What then can you expect by publiſhing any thing but Scorn and Contempt? For many will be apt to ſay, what meaneth this <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>gly Pale <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who with his Whimſeys and Trifles buſies our Printers, and creates us much trouble? What (anſwered Neceſſity) Hunger conſtrains him to take ſuch a courſe: For, Mr. <hi>Salgado</hi> (I'm confident) by all Laudable means endeavoureth to eſchew hard Straits, not hunting after Airy Praiſe, and a great Name. Which the one ſaying ſtopt the mouth of Bluſhing Shame.</p>
            <p>Thus being paſt Shame, I do ſet this Treatiſe on the Pillory, <hi>i.e.</hi> I ſtick not to expoſe it to the Cenſures of Carping Criticks. But methinks I hear a great many entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a Diſcourſe to this purpoſe. 'Tis not
<pb facs="tcp:61065:5"/>worth our while to take ſtrict notice of a Poor Diſtreſſed man paſt Shame, ſeeing Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity has no Law.</p>
            <p>Wherefore, moſt Noble, Puiſſant, Anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent and Generous <hi>Engliſh,</hi> or rather Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical Nation (for you are my Tutelar Angels, in regard that theſe five years, and above, I have enjoyed Life and Sanctuary by your Protection and Benigne Generoſity) I preſent you with this Solemnity of the <hi>Bulls</hi> at <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drid,</hi> my Native Soyl. If any thing therein be amiſs, I claim an intereſt in the clemency of your Promiſe; but if otherwiſe, look up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it as a Teſtimony of my undiſſembled Gratitude.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewel.</salute>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:61065:5"/>
         </div>
         <div type="illustration">
            <pb facs="tcp:61065:6"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>a bullfight</figDesc>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Bull a Hunting</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>The Place there: of in Madrid</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>1 <hi>The King and Queene</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2 <hi>The Kings Counsell</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3 <hi>The Embaſsadors</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>4 <hi>The Gentlemen with their Lackeys hunting y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> Bull</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5 <hi>The Young Placito</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6 <hi>The Bulls Stablls</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:61065:7"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:61065:7"/>
            <head>An Impartial and Brief Deſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the <hi>Plaza,</hi> or Sumptuous Market-place of <hi>Madrid,</hi> and the <hi>Bull-baiting</hi> there.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>I Am certiſied by your Letter, that a commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable Curioſity has induced you to Travel through <hi>France, Italy</hi> and <hi>Germany;</hi> adding further, that, had you not been perſwaded to the contrary by a certain perſon, (one who, I'm apt to believe, has no good will to my Country) the Pleaſures and Rarities of <hi>Spain</hi> had not eſcap'd your Impartial and Diligent Conſideration: Aſſure your ſelf, none could be more concerned to enjoy your Fellowſhip there; nor readier to do you good Offices, than I, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on conſideration of the manifold, and ſignal Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligations laid upon me by a perſon of your worth. But ſeeing it is to no purpoſe to repent what is paſt, I ſhall forbear to enlarge on this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject: Yet becauſe you ſeem to be not a little diſſatisfied that you had not the good Fortune of ſeeing <hi>Spain,</hi> and more eſpecially the <hi>Eſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urial,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:61065:8"/>and the yearly Feſtival at <hi>Madrid;</hi> I ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour, according to my Bounden Duty, to ſatisfie your Curioſity in this point; inſomuch, that from your Cloſet you may receive a full view of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Court, and its Magnificence, as alſo the goodly and large Fields of <hi>Madrid,</hi> without expending much, or expoſing your Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon to danger after the manner of moſt Travellers who repair thither; and for your greater clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in the matter, I ſend you this large Scheme.</p>
            <p>In deſcribing the matter in hand, my Stile ſhall be plain, and the Relation Impartial; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that I bear no liking to diſingenuity, or the forging of Romantick Novelties and Fictions.</p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Eſcurial,</hi> we ſhall have a fairer oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity to treat on it at another occaſion: This in the general you may know, that, (according to the unanimous conſent of all who have travel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led thither) it is a thing very well worth the while. Our preſent Diſcourſe then ſhall be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confin'd to the <hi>Bull-baiting</hi> (as it is called) at <hi>Madrid.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It has been the Fate of <hi>Spain,</hi> as that of other Puiſſant Nations, not to have eſcaped <hi>Scot</hi>-free of the frequent, and noiſome In-roads of many Cruel Adverſaries of different Languages, Laws and Conſtitutions; ſo that ſome Veſtigias of the one muſt be ſuppoſed to remain, as well as the other. Thoſe who did bear chief ſway there, were the <hi>Romans, Vandals, Goths</hi> and <hi>Saracens;</hi> inſomuch that the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue appears to be an Aggregate of the <hi>Latine, German</hi> and <hi>Ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick.</hi>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:61065:8"/>The <hi>Saracens</hi> obtaining the lateſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, their Laws and Language leave the deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Impreſſion. Among other their Conſtitutions, this Feſtival which we are about to deſcribe was one.</p>
            <p>You may eaſily object that it is a Cruel and Barbarous Recreation, which I am ready to grant, and ſo much the rather, that its Original is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riv'd from ſuch a Barbarous Rable as the <hi>Turks</hi> were, and are to this day: Nevertheleſs, an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>controull'd Cuſtom of long continuance has given it the force and validity of a Law, and the moſt Honourable deſignation of a Royal Feſtival, which if any perſon of what Quality ſoever, once endeavoured to Rectify, he ſhould inevitably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur the riſque of Reproach and Shame, if not a more ſad Fate. It being therefore altogether extrinſick to any purpoſe and concernment, as a private man to determine any thing againſt the Lawfulneſs and Unlawfulneſs of this Solemnity; I ſhall content my ſelf by making a clear diſcovery thereof, for your greater ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lincolns-Inn-Fields</hi> are neither ſo large, nor ſpacious, as this place of publick reſort at <hi>Madrid,</hi> which is exactly Square, being ſurrounded with Houſes Uniform all along in all their Dimenſions, erected to the Altitude of five pair of Stairs, with a great many moſt Curious Windows, and Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conies over laid with the pureſt Gold. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the Square is Level, to the end that the Foming Bulls, and Prancing Horſes may run their Courſes with the greater eaſineſs and cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity.
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:61065:9"/>From the ground to the firſt pair of Stairs are reared up Theaters made of Timber for the People: The Thirty Balconies ſet apart for the King and Court, are Sumptuouſly Furniſh'd with the Richeſt Tapeſtry and choiceſt Velvet that Money or Art can purchaſe. Here it's obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vable that all Noblemen, whoſe lot it is not to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend the Court for that preſent Quarter, are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the priviledge of theſe Balconies; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſuch perſons may poſſeſs whatever other places they judge moſt convenient. In <hi>Spain</hi> there are divers kinds of Councels, as the King's Councel, that of the <hi>Inquiſition, War, India, Italy,</hi> the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> and <hi>Arragonia,</hi> and conſequently Councellors of different degrees and qualities; for which cauſe it is appointed, that each of thoſe have their Balconies apart, Beautified with Silks and Tapeſtry of Colours differing, according to the diverſity of thoſe Offices and Officers.</p>
            <p>All Ambaſſadors from Foraign Kings and Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentates are Treated after the ſame Faſhion, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept the <hi>Pope</hi>'s Legate, whoſe Modeſty and Piety (forſooth, layes ſuch a reſtraint upon him, that that Prophane Feſtival, not being of the Churches appointment) muſt not be Honoured with his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence. All other ranks of perſons Aſſembled thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, may poſſeſs what Seats they are able to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe: This I ſay, becauſe the general Confluence to this Common Play from all Corners, makes ſuch a Crowd, that notwithſtanding the great num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Theaters, Balconies, and Windows, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:61065:9"/>elſewhere, none can purchaſe a Room in the firſt pair of Stairs, at a lower rate than 200. Crowns, yea and thoſe places which are not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to the Scorching Heat of the Sun after four a Clock, muſt be ſuppoſed to amount to a greater ſum of Money: Above the firſt Row of Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dows, places may be got more eaſily. Seeing this Feſtival falls out yearly in the Months of <hi>June</hi> and <hi>July,</hi> any perſon may imagine that a Refreſhing Shadow cannot be enjoved without much Money and great Moyan, becauſe of the then extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary Heat of this place, which ordinarily is known to be a moſt Hot Climate. In the Cool of the Evening, (a moſt dangerous Seaſon I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs) all perſons promiſcuouſly Throng thither, but chiefly about Ten of the Clock at Night, when the Affections are much delighted with a moſt Sweet Melody and Conſort of Inſtrumental and Vocal Muſick, and all occaſions of that na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the Guitar and Harp are moſt frequently uſed; becauſe generally the <hi>Spaniards</hi> can Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouſly Play on thoſe Inſtruments. Where it's obſervable, that all Muſitians are had in great account at ſuch a time, not reſpecting what per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons they be, which is hardly diſcernable, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that all are diſguis'd by moſt Gorgeous Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel. It is further to be obſerved, that if the Jealous <hi>Spaniard</hi> can eſpy any man Comple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting his Wife with Jocoſe Words or Kiſſes, without any conſideration, he'l Furiouſly Aſſault ſuch a perſon with Sword and Cudgel, whence ariſe many moſt lamentable Tragedies; for the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:61065:10"/>preventing of which, the Law has wiſely ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed a conſiderable number of <hi>Allquaciles,</hi> whom we here call Conſtables, whoſe proper and ſole Office it is, to mediate betwixt thoſe perſons, rewarding them with Bonds and Fetters for the commiſſion of ſuch Horrid Outrages.</p>
            <p>The enſuing day about eight of the Clock in the Morning, no place can be found empty, whileas none of the Members of the Court are preſent, but the Mayor and Aldermen.</p>
            <p>This Morning Game or Recreation (called <hi>Encierro,</hi> or the bringing forth of the <hi>Bull</hi>) is thus performed. There is a Gate in <hi>Madrid, De la vega</hi> by name, nigh to which a large Room is appointed for the Reception of the <hi>Bulls</hi> the day precedeing this Solemn Feaſt, where they are Gently Fed, rather to render them the more Furious, than in the leaſt to ſtrengthen the miſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Creatures. It's certain that for the moſt part, <hi>Bulls</hi> are more Furious in <hi>Spain</hi> than any other part of the World; and there more eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially, ſuch as Feed by the Rivers <hi>Tago</hi> and <hi>Ja<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rama</hi> flowing betwixt <hi>Toledo</hi> and <hi>Madrid.</hi> But to return to our purpoſe; There is a long and ſtraight Street or Lane adjoyning to the Houſe in which the <hi>Bulls</hi> are ſhut up, and terminating in the place of publick reſort, where all Paſſages are carefully ſtopt, only over againſt the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid Street there is another large Room left wide open, whether the Mad Animals do Throng, finding no other place of refuge left them; by which means a moſt eaſie courſe is contrived for
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:61065:10"/>leading them forth to the Slaughter. I ſhall not detain you longer by relating other Paſſiges of the <hi>Encierro;</hi> for its a matter ſcarce worth our while, as being deſtitute of Order and Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by reaſon of the Courts Abſence. About two of the Clock in the Afternoon twelve <hi>Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diators</hi> repair to the place, where all are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Fight whom Magnanimity, or Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhall excite thereto; which Liberty would unqueſtionably produce Sad Tragedies, if full Goals and Empty Purſes were not ſufficient means to ſtop ſuch Diſorders. Two hours after, there appear the Nobility in their Stately Coaches, all the ground being Sprinkled over with Water, becauſe of the Burning Heat of the <hi>Sun.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which while its a Setting, the King and Court, with the Councellors and Ambaſſadors are to be ſeen to the great ſatisfaction of all perſons. Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the back of this the Royal Conſtables, being twelve in number, in good Equipage, and moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on Horſes with the Richeſt Harneſs imagin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, drive away all perſons and Diſorders; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch, that in a very ſhort time the Conſtables are to be ſeen and none elſe in the plain Square. Afterwards twenty and four Hogsheads of Water are carried in Waggons, reſembling ſo many green Mountains, becauſe of their bigneſs, and being covered over with moſt Fragrant Herbs; thoſe large Veſſels are the Seats of twenty four men, who, upon demand, open the Bung-Holes, ſo that in an Inſtant the whole Plain is Beſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with Water. In the next place, the Kings Life-Guard
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:61065:11"/>conſiſting of 100. <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and as many <hi>Germans,</hi> attend His Majeſty all along, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Armed with Halberts; whom Coats of Red and Yellow Silk, and Caps of the choiceſt Black Velvet, adorn exceedingly.</p>
            <p>By this time methinks you have got a pretty clear <hi>Idea</hi> of what is Antecedaneous to the main thing in hand: So that, if the moſt Stately Bal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conies and Theaters, if the vaſt number of People, if the Nobility Gorgeouſly (I had ſaid wonder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully) Arrayed, if the Kings Conſtables main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining good Order, if in the laſt place His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Life-Guard: I ſay, if each, and all of thoſe be Impartially Canvaſſed by ſuch a Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derative perſon as you are; I doubt not but you'l be conſtrain'd upon the moſt ſolid grounds and reaſons imaginable to joyn with me in the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendation of this Feſtival beyond any Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the World. I confeſs <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Italy</hi> Vaunt very much of their Splended Games, (as they call them) and the <hi>Engliſh</hi> upon more juſt grounds extol the Coſtlineſs of their Prizes, and the Statelineſs of their Courſing-Horſes: But in my humble Opinion, what I'm a deſcribing, may claim right to the Preheminence. Yet, if what has been hitherto ſaid cannot ſufficiently evince the Truth of this point, I ſhall endeavour to drive out one Foming Bull, that by ſeeing the reſult of ſuch an Enterpriſe, your Curioſity may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the greater ſatisfaction.</p>
            <p>We told you that the <hi>Bull</hi> was ſhut up in a large Room, therefore the perſon, whoſe undaunted
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:61065:11"/>Courage or Boldneſs ſets him a work to Encounter with this Raging Creature, ſtands to his Poſture at the Door of the ſaid Houſe with a long and ſharp-pointed Launce in his Hand, having one of his Knees ſet to the ground: Immediatly after the Sound of a Trumpet, a Conſtable runs with all poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible ſpeed, and ſets the Door of the Room, where the Furious Animal is encloſed, wide open. Way being thus made, and all perſons Attentively look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on, the man is by and by Aſſaulted with great Violence, which on-ſet, if by Dexterity or good luck, he can evade; there is a fair occaſion preſented him for Killing or Wounding the <hi>Bull</hi> to purpoſe; which if he miſs to do, his Life or Members are in Jeopar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. It's a thirſting deſire after ſome imaginary Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour that ſets ſuch Bold Fellows upon the expoſing of themſelves to thoſe dangerous circumſtances, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther than the advantage of getting the Beaſts which they have Killed, or Wounded to purpoſe.</p>
            <p>That the next <hi>Bull</hi> may be rendred the more Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, they ſet up a quantity of Wool, in Figure repreſenting a man, with a conſiderable weight at his Legs; which while the Beaſt puſheth in a moſt formidable manner, the weight keeps it in a ſtraight Poſition, by which means the <hi>Bull</hi> is wonderfully enraged. Sometimes a very deſpicable Peaſant is ſet upon a Lean Deformed Horſe, and expoſed very often to a Violent Death, becauſe of his Antago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts Strength and Rage. For dragging out the <hi>Bulls</hi> once Killed, ſix <hi>Mules</hi> of divers Colours are ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed, which, by the conduct of four men, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh this work with all poſſible Velocity and Artifice. Six Foot-men are ordain'd to Encounter
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:61065:12"/>with the four Beaſts yet remaining, to whom no other Weapon is granted, but a Dagger with ſome few <hi>Rexones</hi> in a Bagg, which in length exceed not ſix or ſeven Inches, having Hafts well ordered with Bunches of Garlands, and Points exceeding ſharp for the more ready carrying on of the Intendment. Such as be thus Stated are commonly moſt dextrous, whom it behooves to Fight with the <hi>Bull</hi> Face to Face; he who doth otherwiſe, will undoubtedly incur the riſque of Impriſonment, with moſt abaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Reproaches, and the loſs of a conſiderable Prize. Some men are ſo Nimble, that by a Gentle motion they can eaſily evade the <hi>Bulls</hi> Fury, and at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain their deſign. Thus matters go on until ſuch time as the Trumpet Sound; then Butchers-Dogs, and men Armed with Broad-Swords quickly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>patch the Strength and Violence of thoſe formidable Animals.</p>
            <p>Some years ago I remember upon an occaſion of this kind to have ſeen a thing admirable indeed, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Young man of Twenty years Encountring with a big <hi>Bull,</hi> eſcaped all his Comminations by the Nimble and Dextrous motion of his Leg; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he did ſpring upon his Back, and catching hold of his Left Horn, Wounded him in ſeveral places with the <hi>Rexones:</hi> In which Poſture he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued until the Trumpet was about to Sound, then (and not till then) he diſpatched the Foaming <hi>Bull</hi> with his Dagger, having ſuſtain'd no prejudice ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginable. All perſons preſent were poſſeſt with a wonderful Opinion of the Youth, becauſe of his ſurpaſſing Agility, Courage, Dexterity and Bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. But ſeeing this example is remarkable, we ſhall inſiſt on it at greater length hereafter.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:61065:12"/>
            <p>It will not be amiſs here to mention what fell out upon ſuch an occaſion as this in the preſence of <hi>Charles</hi> the firſt, of Bleſſed Memory: Who, while Prince of <hi>Wales,</hi> repaired to the Court of <hi>Spain,</hi> whether to be Married to the <hi>Infanta,</hi> or upon what other deſign, I cannot well determine: How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever all Comedies, Playes and Feſtivals, (this of the <hi>Bulls</hi> at <hi>Madrid</hi> being included, were appointed to be as decently and Manificently gone about, as poſſible, for the more Sumptuous and Stately En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of ſuch a Splended Prince. Therefore after three <hi>Bulls</hi> had been Killed, and the fourth a coming forth, there appeared four Gentlemen in good Equipage; not long after a Brisk Lady in moſt Gorgeous Apparel, attended with perſons of Quality, and ſome three or four Grooms walked all along the Square a Foot. Aſtoniſhment Seized upon the Beholders that one of the Female Sex could aſſume the unheard Boldneſs of expoſing her ſelf to the violence of the moſt Furious Beaſt yet ſeen, which had overcome, yea almoſt Killed two men of great Strength, Courage and Dexterity. Inconti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently the <hi>Bull</hi> ruſhed towards the Corner where the Lady and her Attendants ſtood, ſhe (after all had fled) drew forth her Dagger very unconcernedly, and thruſt it moſt dextrouſly into the <hi>Bulls</hi> Neck, having catched hold of his Horn; by which ſtroak, without any more trouble, her deſign was brought to Perfection; after which, turning about towards the King's Balcony, ſhe made her Obeyſance, and withdrew her ſelf in ſuitable State and Gravity. Sir, did you ever ſee or hear, any example to parallel this? Wonderful indeed! that a Faint-hearted feeble
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:61065:13"/>Woman (one would think) ſhould ſtand in the Fields Undauntedly, after her Attendants had quickly made their eſcape, yea and have overcome ſuch a Furious Creature as that <hi>Bull</hi> was. This be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a matter of Fact, which I thus branch forth into divers circumſtances; I hope my Fate ſhall not be ſo bad, as to be called a Lyar: Nevertheleſs, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that I judge you one of my beſt Friends. I will not conceal the Myſtery of the matter from you. This perſon was a man, though in the Habit of a Woman, of gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at Experience, Agility, and Reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, who had been well inured to this hard Labour at ſeveral other occaſions, whom they appointed to be diſguiſed ſo much the rather, that the Prince of <hi>Wales</hi> might be the more taken with the thing. But not inſiſting further on this, I ſhall proceed to the remaining part of my Relation with all Brevity and Perſpicuity poſſible.</p>
            <p>Noblemen of ſingular Magnanimity, being moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted on Horſes, incomparable Nimble and Pretty, with coſtly Harneſs beſeeming the Dignity of their Riders, and the Splendor of the Feſtival; appear in great State and Pomp. Whoſe Grooms in a moſt decent manner carry the Launces with which their Maſters intend to diſpatch the <hi>Bulls.</hi> (Their Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince and Charge is to irritate the Rage and Fury of the formidable beaſt) Thoſe Heroick minds ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naging their Launces moſt Dexterouſly, accompliſh their Noble purpoſes very often by Killing or Wounding the Foaming Animals: Which if they fail to do, then the Horſes ſuſtain great prejudice, in ſo much that their Riders are Diſmounted, whom it behooves in that caſe to Encounter with the <hi>Bulls</hi>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:61065:13"/>a Foot, Laſhing them with Broad-Swords; which if any decline to do, he is Baffled, and Branded with the Character of Puſillanimity and Cowardice. You may eaſily imagine that Generous Spirits will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer Death to ſuch an Ignomy and Repr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ach. Thus three or four perſons of Quality continue until it be pretty late, at which time they drive out a <hi>Bull</hi> co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered all over with Artificial Fire, by which he is rendered moſt Furious and Hurtful: For Curioſity and want of further order, induces the Rable to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach ſo near unto him, that by his moſt dreadful puſhings many ſuſtain Mutilation, yea and Death it ſelf; in ſo much that a Tragedy is often times the Concluſion of this Solemnity.</p>
            <p>In the laſt place of this Relation it may be worth the while to give a brief Account of a notable in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Folly in a Young Lady, and Paſſionate Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merity in three Gallants, while the King and No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility were preſent. Three Gentlemen, <hi>Marcus An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonius, Charles</hi> and <hi>Lodovicus</hi> fell over Head and Ears in Love with a certain Lady of good Extract and Education, being the only Child of her Parents, and then about the Age of Twenty Years, whoſe Name was <hi>Margareta.</hi> Thoſe Rivals could hardly look upon one another without Menaces and blows, of whom while any one endeavoured, after the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Cuſtom, to make a Sweet Pleaſant Melody in the Hearing of the Lady, then the other two di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbed him; which did breed many and great Quarrellings in the Streets each Night, inſomuch that the Ladies Parents and all others dwelling nigh that place, were highly offended; which when <hi>Margareta</hi> had Eſpyed, having (it ſeems) very
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:61065:14"/>little Affection for any of them; directed Letters to them ſeverally, for preventing of all ſuch Diſorders for the future; of which Epiſtles the ſum and Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor follows.</p>
            <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <hi>I Cannot be induced to believe that</hi> Muſick <hi>accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with ſcandalous Diſturbances, can be termed a Teſtimony of ſincere Affection; yea, it ſeems that you aim more by ſuch a courſe to diſgrace and baffle my Name; than to teſtify any real reſpect to my Perſon: Therefore I earneſtly intreat you may be pleaſed to deſiſt from ſuch a Fooliſh, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nmannerly and Scandalous Action. But if all this cannot be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient to put a ſtop to the Folly of your Exorbitant Affections, I ſhall poſe you with this experiment. Whoever reſolves to expreſs his Dexterity, Courage and Agility to all Beholders ſufficiently, and his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Love toward me, let him Buckle with the</hi> Bull <hi>to Morrow in preſence of all the Aſſembly, and he who ſhall be ſo Fortunate as to cut off his Neck, and preſent me with his Horns, may be aſſured by my Subſcription, that I ſhall not decline to own him for my Husband: Which if any or all of you refuſe to do, get you gone; for Effeminate men are none of thoſe I aim at, or deſire to be joyned unto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <salute>Farewel</salute>
                     <signed>from <hi>Margareta.</hi>
                     </signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>This pertinent and ſmart Letter Non plus'd all the Rivals, ſeeing thereby a Province was preſcribed them, which they never dreamed of, nor judged
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:61065:14"/>any ways Honourable; becauſe Noblemen (ſuch as thoſe were) how dextrous ſoever they be, are never deſired to Graſp with the <hi>Bull</hi> a Foot, and very ſeldom on Horſeback; yet notwithſtanding all oppoſition and Reluctancy, leſt they ſhould be branded with the deteſtable Character of Pufilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, they unanimouſly conſented to the Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, each of them ſignifying a part by a moſt Paſſionate Letter, that he was abſolutely determin'd to ſatisfy her demand, or die. Wherefore, till the time appointed, they remained with the Rable, that more eaſie and ſpeedy Acceſs might be attained to appear in the performance of a thing in which their Credit was ſo nearly concerned, where they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed themſelves, until the Noble-men well Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted were about to Encounter with the fifth <hi>Bull;</hi> at which time <hi>Marcus Antonius</hi> ſteping down, got moſt Nimbly on the <hi>Bull's</hi> back, intending by that means to diſpatch him quickly with his Broad Sword. Next to him appeared <hi>Charles,</hi> whoſe buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and work it was to Catch hold of the Peaſts Horns, which fell out ſo Fortunately, according to his deſire and deſign, that the <hi>Bull</hi> ſtumbled by the firſt Aſſault; ſo that <hi>Antonius</hi> fell to the ground. <hi>Lodovicus,</hi> eſpying <hi>Charles</hi> ſticking faſt to the Horns, and <hi>Antonius</hi> Diſmounted, with a Dexterous and Seaſonable ſtroke, cut off the <hi>Bulls</hi> Neck. <hi>Charles</hi> immediatly got to the Lady with the Head, ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying that the condition of the Compact was ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filled, and therefore he claimed an Intereſt in her for his Wife. <hi>Lodovicus</hi> did take it very ill to be thus Trapan'd by Subtle <hi>Charles,</hi> ſeeing he it was who cut off the Neck, and therefore concluded the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:61065:15"/>Prize to be his in all Juſtice. <hi>Antonius</hi> moreover being the perſon who gave firſt proof of his Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity, (making way for the other two) concluded it highly reaſonable that he ſhould be preferr'd be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore either of them. Which did breed ſuch a wrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling among them, that had not the <hi>Alquaciles</hi> or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtables interpos'd, they would have committed a moſt lamentable Tragedy; being now led to the King, they give an Account of the matter, which when His Majeſty heard, he commended, in ſome reſpect, their Valour, but could not approve of their Incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderateneſs; ſeeing therefore he underſtood it to be Vanity, if not Cruelty, in the Fooliſh Lady, rather than any ſincere Love, to demand ſuch a dangerous attempt; ſtrict Orders were given that none of the Rivals ſhould perſiſt or proceed in a courſe ſo very Fooliſh. Thus the debate ended.</p>
            <p>We have now Impartially deſcribed what is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable in the yearly Feſtival at <hi>Madrid.</hi> I grant indeed, (as before) that it is a recreation ſcarcely beſeeming Chriſtians, whoſe meekneſs and Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs ſhould not admit of ſuch Barbarous Diverſions. Nevertheleſs, (to ſpeak no more of that) it is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally concluded, that perſons appointed for ſuch an Exerciſe, ought to be furniſhed, not only with ſuitable Courage, but alſo with Agility and Dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terity, to evade the Aſſaults of a Violent Brute, by which means many become Famous.</p>
            <p>Here we may obſerve how much the <hi>Roman</hi> Playes come ſhort of this Game: For Criminals were th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re compell'd to Graple with <hi>Boars</hi> and <hi>Lyons</hi> moſt Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culent Creatures, of which few can promiſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves the Victory; and thus poor Convicted Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:61065:15"/>ſuffered a moſt Cruel Death: To which it may be added, that thoſe Games were chiefly deſigned to ſatisfy the Bloody and Vindictive Humours of the people, who rejoyced in ſuch lamentable experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. It is otherwiſe here, in regard that no man is conſtrain'd to undergo this hard labour; neither are Criminals puniſhed with ſuch a Death; but Maſculine and Noble Minds deſire an occaſion of this kind, whereby proof may be given of their Agility and Undaunted Courage. However (as I told in the beginning) it is not my work to praiſe or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demn this moſt Ancient and Uncontrolled Cuſtom. All I aim'd at was, to ſatisfy your commendable Curioſity by deſcribing this Feſtival, which is judg'd in <hi>Spain</hi> a moſt Noble Recreation. Our next buſinſs ſhall be to enlarge a little on the Hiſtory of <hi>Placidus,</hi> of whom mention was made elſewhere.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>
                  <hi>The Hiſtory of</hi> Placidus.</head>
               <p>THis <hi>Placidus</hi> (a youth very much admir'd and prais'd becauſe of his Valiant Exploits) was the Son of <hi>Fadrique</hi> who play'd the Merchant with one <hi>Antonius</hi> in <hi>Sevil,</hi> a City in <hi>Spain</hi> well known, and much commended by Travellers of all Nations and Languages who reſort thither.</p>
               <p>Undaunted Courage ſet our <hi>Placidus</hi> a work to Graple with a moſt Violent Brute, after he had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained ſometime in <hi>Madrid,</hi> whether he repaired without the knowledge and Conſent of his Indul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Parents for this very end, that in the Flower of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:61065:16"/>his Age, all perſons from the King to the Peaſant, might receive a ſufficient (I may ſay wonderful) Specimen of his ſurpaſſing Fortitude and Magna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimity.</p>
               <p>Here its obſervable, that <hi>Fadrique</hi> and his Hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Son ſeemed rather to be one Perſon, than two; for in Nature, Demeanour, Stature, Speech and Countenance, they reſembled one another ſo much, that a quick-ſighted man could hardly diſtinguiſh betwixt them: Yea, although the Father was a man of 50. and the Son but of 20 years, yet any who look'd upon their Pictures, affirmed ſtiffly that the one was an exact Pattern to the other: And had not the Eyes of men been a demonſtration to the contrary, I am apt to believe that the poſſibility of ſuch an univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal ſimilitude (ſo to call it) would be thought a <hi>Chymaera.</hi> Yet if we conſult Authors of good Note and great worth, many inſtances of this kind may be found.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Valer. Max.</hi> with great Confidence affirms that <hi>Pompey</hi> the Great, <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>relius</hi> and <hi>Publeius Libertinus</hi> differed in nothing, but their Veſtments; ſo that if two of them were Arrayed after the ſame Faſhion, a quick-ſighted perſon could not aſſign a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence betwixt them. It is alſo written by <hi>Pliny,</hi> that two Boys (the one being a <hi>Syrian,</hi> and the other a <hi>French</hi>) were ſo very like to one another in every point, that a certain perſon ſold them to <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cus Antonius</hi> under the notion of Brethren. <hi>Anto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi> perceiving their Language to differ, Threatned the perſon who had thus impos'd on him, to whom the other replyed, <hi>If they had been Brethren, I would not require ſo great a ſum of Money, becauſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:61065:16"/>in that caſe Nature could not be ſaid to bring forth ſo great a wonder, as now you ſee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If it be true in any reſpect, that (according to the <hi>Philoſopher</hi>) ſimilitude begets Affection, how much more in this inſtance of <hi>Fadrique</hi> and <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> whoſe mutual love was wonderful beyond that of moſt perſons in ſuch a Relation. Yet by the Interpoſition of <hi>Agnes,</hi> a Young Lady of ſingular Endowments and Education, the Brightneſs of this Splendid Paſſion ſuffered in ſome meaſure an Eclipſe. This Beautiful Object became the Center of their Deſires and incontaminate Love, which could not be ſmothered long: Wherefore they diſcovered their Maladies to one another in a moſt Friendly manner, and determined (after a Serious and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture conſultation) to ſubmit the event of the matter in hands to the Young Ladies and her Mothers Arbitrement; inſomuch that the perſon excluded, ſhould remove from his Native Country, leſt by his Preſence way might be made for Jealouſy, whoſe effects are more dangerous no where, than in <hi>Spain.</hi> After this both of them met with bad Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and ſmall Encouragement at the hands of <hi>Agnes</hi> and her Mother: Yet in Proceſs of time <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driques</hi> Riches and Conſtancy, had great influence on the Matron. It is true the Youth of <hi>Placidus</hi> was no ſmall motive to obtain the reſpect of the Pretty Lady: Nevertheleſs Baggs of Money were an Argument <hi>a fortiore.</hi> After both Parties had pondered ſedately the Circumſtances moſt remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, the Mother ſpeaks to her Daughter after this manner.</p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:61065:17"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>My Dear Child, you ſee there is no Solid Objection which can be brought againſt thoſe Worthy Perſons who have ſet their Affections on you; and therefore, I judge it moſt reaſonable, that you freely declare your own Sentiments in this Affair. I know the Neatneſs and Youth of</hi> Placidus, <hi>will have great weight with you; and on the other hand</hi> Fadrique<hi>'s declining Age will in ſome meaſure alienate your Affections from him: But hearken diligently my Daughter to the Dictates of right Reaſon, rather than fond Fancy, which miſleads many in your Circumſtances; and you ſhall find Riches, and Experience more eligible, than undaunted Youth, or any other imaginary founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, on which the Superſtructure of your Deſires and Deſigns are fixed. That this may yet have the greater weight in your eſtimation, conſider how much Riches contribute to beget Eſteem and Honour in this City where we live; So that Perſons of Noble Extract, loſe their Dignity frequently with their Wealth. What is Beauty but a Fading Flower, which Nature in a ſhort time, or ſome unexpected Accident will prey up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and reduce to nothing? Let a Brisk Gallant diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge to admiration all the Punctilio's of Court-Edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation and Activity; will that purchaſe Food and Raiment? Whereas Money Anſwers all things; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out which Trading and Commerce ſhould die. I judge it ſuperfluous to make an enumeration of the qualities of Gold which we Eat, and with which we are cloathed: Hence aroſe the Proverb,</hi> That is Gold which is pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed by Gold; <hi>which ſaying renders it moſt uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſal, ſeeing all things are valued at ſome rate or other. It is true, I confeſs,</hi> Placidus <hi>is inferior to few Gentlemen in Probity and Reputation; but its as
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:61065:17"/>true, his Father, (though Rich) has many Children, and may in all probability beget many more; what then will the Riches amount to, which muſt be divided among ſo many? You know if it were poſſible to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide the Ocean into many Rivulets, this vaſt Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of Waters would appear very inconſiderable, in reſpect of what it now is. But I paſs by this Topick; lest that you may ſuſpect Intereſt prevails with me. In the next place therefore, let us conſider whether or no you can promiſe your ſelf as great ſatisfaction in the one, as the other: Not at all; for, whoever is Married to</hi> Placidus, <hi>muſt neceſſarily be in a Slaviſh ſubjection to his Father, his Brethren, Siſters and Relations; whereas the Wife of</hi> Fadrique <hi>will enjoy Immunity from ſuch a bitter lot, as being above and beyond the reach of all thoſe Cenſurers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alas! alas! Woful experience the School-miſtriſs of Fools, has furniſhed me with this Obſervation; as witneſs thoſe Gray-Hairs, brought forth untimouſly by Exceſſive Grief and Sorrow. Shall you deck your ſelf with the Fineſt Needle-Work, and moſt Gorgeous Raiment poſſible; then Black-mouth'd Back-biters will readily miſconſtrue your Neatneſs. If on the other hand, ſuch a decorum be neglected, why (ſay they) ſhe is not content with her Lot and Condition. You cannot frequent Divine Worſhip without the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of Levity or Hypocriſy, nor forbear ſuch a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Obſervance; but immediatly occaſion will be taken of branding you with the ſtigma of an Irreligi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous wretch. In fine, the Eyes of all Relations will be ſixed upon you, that you cannot promiſe your ſelf Satisfaction and Tranquility in the moſt minute cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance. And it may be added further, that ſuch
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:61065:18"/>an uncharitable multitude may ſo influence your Hus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band with prejudice, that in a very ſhort time, the greateſt of all your Miſeries ſhall ariſe from his Jeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſy or unbeſeeming carriage towards you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>If ſo be then, that by being Eſpouſed to</hi> Fadrique, <hi>no ſuch Inconveniencies can in reaſon be ſuſpected; what remains, but that in obedience to thoſe preſſing Arguments of your Loving Mother, and in relation to your own future Contentment, you cheerfully aſſent to the Propoſals of the Father without the leaſt Reluctan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy imaginable.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thoſe Pithy motives founded on Reaſon and Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, wrought a ſenſible and ſuddain change upon <hi>Agnes;</hi> inſomuch, that in a thundring manner, ſhe decided the whole matter in Favours of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drique;</hi> which concluſion produced no leſs Sorrow to <hi>Placidus,</hi> than Contentment and Joy to <hi>Fadrique.</hi> Whereupon dejected <hi>Placidus,</hi> (according to his Paſſion) without any more delay, forſook his Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive Country, having got from his Father about 1000 <hi>Guinies,</hi> who left it to his choice to ſuſpend his time in <hi>India, Italy,</hi> or the <hi>Low-Countries,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to receive Money upon Bill according to the Cuſtom and Neceſſity of Gentlemen while Abroad.</p>
               <p>When he had come to <hi>Naples</hi> in <hi>Italy,</hi> his Genius inclined him to play the Souldier, as being an Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, by which Honour and laſting Renown is moſt attainable. After a few Months there, he enjoyn'd his Truſtee to certifie <hi>Fadrique</hi> and all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations of <hi>Placidus</hi> Death, that Entercourſe of Letters might be ſtop'd, which he judged the fitteſt courſe and method to free him from Penſive Melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholly; but all this could not Eradicate a Paſſion ſo deeply rooted.</p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:61065:18"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fadrique</hi> by Succeſsful Traffique attained quickly to vaſt Poſſeſſions, which with a Virtuous Wife, might be ſuppoſed a Pleaſant Condition. Yet, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding all this, the want of Children was matter of great Grief to him: Wherefore, (that his Memory might not die with himſelf) he reſolves, without delay, to diſtribute his Riches among his Nephews, <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Bernard,</hi> who are brought to him for that purpoſe. Their Uncle and his Lady Entertain the Boyes with all the Expreſſions of Joy and Kindneſs poſſible. In a very ſhort time their good Behaviour and Affability did procure unto them a great many Friends and Acquaintances in <hi>Sevil,</hi> where they paſs under the Notion of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>driques</hi> Sons. The Old mans love to his Nephews roſe to ſo much the greater height, that he perceived himſelf decaying more ſenſibly than could be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected by the courſe of Nature, not being as yet 60 years, whereas <hi>Agnes</hi> appeared more Brisk than ever.</p>
               <p>Thus <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Bernard</hi> diſcerning that their Uncle had in a manner centered the Comfort and Tranquility of his Decript Old-Age on them, waxed Inſolent and Diſreſpectful towards <hi>Agnes,</hi> whoſe Prudence taught her to obviat the very beginning of this evil, by repreſenting ſuch Enormities to her Indulgent Husband, The Old man complying with his Wife, appointed a Lodging elſewhere for his Nephews, with all things neceſſary, and ſuitable to their Condition: which courſe no ways abated the Inſolence of the Young men, but rather increaſed the ſame; inſomuch that they branded <hi>Agnes</hi> with Incontinency, and many other Vitious qualities.</p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:61065:19"/>
               <p>At this time <hi>Placidus</hi> (having Travelled all <hi>Italy</hi> over) came to <hi>Bononia,</hi> where his Life was in Jeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pardy: For happening to be late out of his Lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, the ſecond or third night after he came to Town, he wandred in the Streets by reaſon of Darkneſs, and his Unacquaintedneſs with the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Corners of the City; at length eſpyed in a place, ſome what remote, a Glimmering Light, whether when he had approached, three Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throats are found Aſſaulting one Gentleman with all poſſible Fury. The Compaſſionate <hi>Placidus</hi> think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that a fit ſeaſon for Charity and Fortitude, became the Oppreſſed Gentlemans Aſſiſtant, by which means two of the Rogues were Grievouſly Wounded, the third being Smote with the Edge of the Sword.</p>
               <p>Having thus Reſcued the <hi>Italian</hi> from Eminent Death, not without ſome danger (for he ſuſtained the prejudice of 2 or 3 Wounds) he calls his Servant to bring his Horſe. <hi>James Viteli,</hi> in whoſe behalf he had Seaſonably appeared: Anſwered, ſaying, <hi>Sir, Your Ineffable Kindneſs and Courage calls for my Attendance as a Servant, who am ready and willing to wait upon all opportunities, whereby I may expreſs my Gratitude. I know diligent ſearch will be made for us by and by; therefore (ſeeing I take you to be a Stranger unacquainted with this City) I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat you may be pleaſed to accept of my Company; and by the Grace of God, we ſhall eſcape the Rage and Fury of our Adverſaries; and I promiſe to Dreſs and Cure your Wounds in a very ſhort time. Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> concluded it highly Reaſonable to lay hold on ſuch a good motion: Wherefore <hi>James Viteli</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducted
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:61065:19"/>him from one Street to another, until at laſt he came to an Houſe, where, it's probable, he had been known; upon which conſideration, he knocks hard at the door, until ſuch time as a comly Youth had given him acceſs; forthwith, (according to his duty and promiſe) he dreſſed the wounds of <hi>Pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidus,</hi> which were not deep nor deadly; enjoyning withal that the Student ſhould go in all haſt to ſuch a Street by name, and return with one exact account of all emergents: whether when the young man had come, he ſees all things in a hurly-burly, one man being dead, on whom a great number of Citi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zens are gazing; and orders given to apprehend ſuch as could be ſuſpected any way acceſſary to ſuch an Aſſaſſination. Where alſo he heard a certain perſon impriſoned, confeſſing that he was the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of one <hi>Placidus,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> who had killed the man. When the Youth returned, he gave an impartial account of all occurrences obſerved by him. The Gentlemen perceiving what might be the reſult of ſuch a commotion, ſlipt away quietly, in regard that they concluded it moſt dangerous to ſtay ſo near the place of Juſtice, where a ſtrict ſearch was to be made.</p>
               <p>Having thus eſcaped hazard, <hi>Placidus</hi> is curious to know the original of his companions misfortune, in being aſſaulted by three men in ſuch a place. To whom <hi>Viteli</hi> anſwered thus:</p>
               <p>My deareſt <hi>Placidus,</hi> I determine to diſcloſe this ſecret to no man living, yet conſidering you to be my greateſt friend upon earth, who in my cauſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed your Noble Perſon to danger; (and negle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting all the important affairs which induced you to
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:61065:20"/>ſee <hi>Bononia</hi>) has continued my companion in af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction (tho' a Stranger) I ſay upon theſe, and many other weighty conſiderations (which my ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low brain cannot comprehend, nor my ſtammering tongue expreſs) I will with the greateſt candour and ingenuity imaginable, diſcover this matter to you.</p>
               <p>I was born at <hi>Rome,</hi> the Queen and Miſtreſs of the World, where (when I was very young) my Honourable Parents gave up the Ghoſt. After that I had ſucked in the firſt and common principles of Learning, my good Friends and Relations ſent me to the famous Univerſity of <hi>Bononia,</hi> where I made no deſpicable proficiency in Philoſophy, and all the Languages profeſſed there, which are the <hi>Spaniſh, German, French, Hebrew</hi> and <hi>Greek:</hi> All which could not ſatiate my thirſting deſires after Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, until the ſtudy of Phyſick became my work and buſineſs. But a Lady of ſingular Endowments and Quality, being pleaſed to honour me with the ſtrongeſt Teſtimonies of ſincere affection, diverted my thoughts from proſecuting the moſt pleaſant of all Studies. How ſecret ſoever this matter was kept, the Ladies Brother underſtood it; which prompted him, with two other Conſpirators, to lie in wait for my Life: and undoubtedly had become a prey to their Fury, if (by the Divine Providence) one of the three had not ſignified to me the method of this moſt horrid Plot.</p>
               <p>Then I determined to travel through <hi>Spain</hi> and other Countries, but (being driven from <hi>Genoa</hi> by a moſt violent Tempeſt) I was enſlaved to the <hi>Turks,</hi> who firſt brought me to <hi>Argiers,</hi> and then
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:61065:20"/>to <hi>Conſtantinople,</hi> where I was ſold very often un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the notion of a Slave. At length I am preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to one of <hi>Mahomet's</hi> Phyſitians, who finding me pretty expert in the principles of Medicine, was pleaſed to encourage me with his Fellowſhip and In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, to my great advantage (I muſt confeſs) in ſome reſpects; whoſe gentleneſs was ſuch, that he would not thwart my inclinations of returning to <hi>Italy,</hi> but rather encouraged me by the Gift of 2000 Guinies.</p>
               <p>After a tedious and dangerous Voyage, I came to <hi>Venice,</hi> where (being unknown) the People look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed upon many of my Operations and Experiments as Miracles, rather than the product of natural Knowledge; for which cauſe the Magiſtrates en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged me with promiſes of a very conſiderable Salary. But all this could not induce me to ſtay, ſeeing my thoughts and deſires were much cencerned with returning to <hi>Bononia,</hi> where I had enjoyed ſo many pleaſant daies. I could not imagin that it was poſſible for any in that place to know me after the abſence of ſix compleat years; which time alſo might quench the ardour of <hi>Camilla</hi>'s paſſion (Ah! her name cannot be concealed, nor my love towards her ſuppreſt.) Upon thoſe conſiderations I came to <hi>Bononia,</hi> where I was entertained with great Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie by all perſons of knowledge, to whom I diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered my various misfortunes and difficulties; by which means the noiſe of my being in Town came to the hearing of <hi>Camilla;</hi> who incontinently ſaluted me by a moſt pathetical Letter, as you may eaſily imagin. Thus our love was renewed; and ſo much the more, becauſe ſhe came the enſuing day diſguiſed to my
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:61065:21"/>Chamber, where we entertained a moſt comfortable Dialogue founded on the ſolid hopes of obtaining our longed for deſires. I ſeemed to decline and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the profeſſion of Medicine in the Univerſity of <hi>Bononia,</hi> meerly, that <hi>Camilla</hi>'s Brother, and his Aſſociates, might not in the leaſt ſuſpect me whom they hated with an inveterate hatred, which time nor dignity could not eradicate. Nevertheleſs, by debating, I obtained the honour of that place. Then Engines of Cruelty are ſet a work to diſpatch me ſome way or another: and (I muſt confeſs) the Rogues had accompliſhed their corrupt deſign, if by the Divine Providence, your ſeaſonable Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity and Magnanimity had not reſcued my Life from their malice. In Teſtimony therefore of my gratitude, I proteſt to remain your moſt faithful friend and Servant while I breath, declaring to that end a willingneſs of accompanying you to <hi>Spain,</hi> or any where elſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Placidus</hi> was very much taken with the grateful acknowledgments, and proteſtations of laſting kindneſs, ſo pitifully expreſſed by <hi>Viteli:</hi> Yet, (being unwilling to divulge or diſcloſe the hidden ſorrow which burdened his ſpirit) he anſwered the other in a moſt courtly and complementing ſtrain. Sir, you may confidently aſſure your ſelf of my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alterable good-will, where-ever you be, or how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever ſtated. The pregnant <hi>Viteli,</hi> by a groan at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending thoſe words, perceived <hi>Placidus</hi> to be a little diſcompoſed: wherefore he reſolved to know the cauſe of ſo great grief at a more ſeaſonable oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion. In the meanwhile, they entred into a ſtrict League of Amity, having all things common; in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:61065:21"/>which real kindneſs conſiſts (if we hear the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher). A few daies after they come to <hi>Genoa</hi> where (as all along their Perigrination) their thoughts were alleviated, by giving an impartial and free account to one another of their diverſe miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunes, and ſo much the more, in regard that <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teli,</hi> by his ſuperlative knowledge, and jocoſe brisk diſpoſition, was a Phyſitian no leſs capable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move the ſorrows of the mind, than the Diſtempes of the body. Yet <hi>Placidus,</hi> in ſome meaſure, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinues dumpiſh and penſive; ſo that <hi>Viteli</hi> intended to expiſcate and extort from him the original and cauſe of ſo laſting a Grief, and did carry all things on in order to his concluſion ſo wittily, that <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> is allured to diſcover the perplexity of his mind, after this manner. Your probity and gentleneſs ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracteth from me a ſecret which I never purpoſed to diſcloſe. After which he makes mention of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drique</hi>'s compact with him, (while both of them had a longing deſire to enjoy the vertuous and beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful <hi>Agnes</hi>) who, by the inſtigation and perſwaſion of her covetous Mother, rejected him, embracing <hi>Fadirque.</hi> In a word, he did not omit the leaſt Punctilio, which could ſatisfie the curioſity of <hi>Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teli;</hi> who replying, anſwered thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>My dear</hi> Placidus, Be of good chear: for there is no Malady ſo great, which admits not of a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy applied with ſo much the better ſucceſs, that the Patient can diſcover his Diſtemper diſtinctly, as you have done, and therefore I conſtantly promiſe (being taught by experience, what ſuch a caſe meaneth) to remove your trouble and grief, by an experiment at firſt (its probable) ſtrange in your
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:61065:22"/>eyes; though, after mature deliberation, moſt obvious. All I crave is, that you condeſcend yet once more, to walk with me in the Streets of <hi>Sevil.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Having thus Embarqued at <hi>Genoa,</hi> they arrived at <hi>Barcelona;</hi> from whence they ſailed by <hi>Tarragona, Valentia, Alicant, Cartagena,</hi> and the borders of <hi>Granada,</hi> until they came to <hi>Malaga,</hi> and at length to <hi>Cadiz,</hi> the Haven of St. <hi>Mary</hi> and St. <hi>Luke,</hi> and ſailed thence all along the River <hi>Betis</hi> to <hi>Sevill;</hi> where (being in ſtrangers apparel) they ſearch for a convenient Lodging; in which <hi>Placidus</hi> abode, while the intelligent <hi>Veteli</hi> went abroad, inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelf, the beſt way he could, about the ſtate of Affairs in <hi>Fadrique</hi>'s Houſe; which he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood exactly, and returned to <hi>Placidus,</hi> ſignifying how indulgent dying <hi>Fadrique</hi> was towards his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolent Nephews, <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Bernard;</hi> as alſo that <hi>Agnes</hi> look't as brisk as ever. In a word, he anſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wered the moſt particular queſtions ſo fully, that <hi>Placidus</hi>'s Grief was in a great meaſure aſſwaged.</p>
               <p>The learned <hi>Viteli</hi> gave ſuch proof of his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge in Phyſick by ſundry wonderful Experiments, that in an inſtant his Name ſpread abroad. <hi>Agnes</hi> therefore hearing of ſuch an expert Phyſitian, thought it her near concernment and duty to conſult with him concerning the nature of <hi>Fadrique</hi>'s diſeaſe which was concluded mortal by all other Phyſitians in <hi>Sevill. Viteli,</hi> having viſited the old man, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned Nature ſhrinking, and Death approaching: Nevertheleſs, to encourage the Lady, he confident<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly affirmed, in the preſence of many Learned and Judicious men, that his Diſeaſe was not mortal;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:61065:22"/>which aſſertion he confirmed with reaſons and argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments founded upon the moſt ſolid and genuine Philoſophy, ſo that no place was left for cavils, all Phyſitians there preſent, being perſwaded of the truth of his Diſcourſe. Which comforted <hi>Agnes</hi> ſo much, that with great intimacy in private Confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, ſhe ſearched into <hi>Viteli</hi>'s ſentiments in this affair. The expert Phyſitian failed not at ſuch a time, to make mention of <hi>Placidus,</hi> whoſe valiant exploits he praiſed with ſuch Eloquence and admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that the Ladies priſtine love revived, and prompted her to enquire very concernedly where he liv'd, and whether there was any truth in the noiſe of his Death. The ſmart <hi>Viteli</hi> by ſuch que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions, perceiving much affection to center in the Ladies breaſt towards <hi>Placidus,</hi> anſwered her thus:</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Madam,</hi> I am obliged to declare the truth, and cannot ſufficiently declare what is true concerning his laſting renown abroad; nor how conſtant and Chriſtian his love has been to you: otherwaies, the exceſſive grief of his ſpirit, had undoubtedly ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred him deſperate, and acceſſary to his own death. The rumour of his Death, implied that his love might be termed dead, becauſe without the hope of enjoying its object.</p>
               <p>God knows (ſaid <hi>Agnes</hi>) how much I deſired to be married to him: but Fortune has ſo ordered, that I ſhould be the Wife of <hi>Fadrique,</hi> though much againſt my inclinations. Yea, I muſt add (ſeeing this Subject is pleaſant) that the love of <hi>Placidus</hi> is of great force with me to this hour. It is true, I am obliged every way to bear a ſuitable reſpect to
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61065:23"/>
                  <hi>Fadrique,</hi> who has continued all along a kind Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, never believing the odd aſperſions with which his inſolent Nephews <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Bernard</hi> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to brand me.</p>
               <p>I know (ſaid <hi>Viteli</hi>) that many Waters cannot quench Love, but it muſt break forth after ſome manner or other. And methinks, the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence has conducted me hither in a good ſeaſon; therefore, ſeeing that I am perſwaded that (ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the courſe of nature) <hi>Fadrique</hi> cannot live fifteen daies. <hi>Madam,</hi> (if you be pleaſed) I ſhall, in the mean time, contrive and carry on matters ſo dextrouſly, that by your Husbands laſt Will, and without the leſt oppoſition, you may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy your beloved <hi>Placidus</hi> inſtead of his Father. I have heard <hi>Fadrique</hi> (replied the Lady) at ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry times, in a moſt pathetical and paſſionate man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner expreſſing ſorrow and grief for the Death of his great, and real friend <hi>Placidus</hi> (as he called him) For (ſaid he) if my Son were alive, I would diſpoſe of my ſubſtance to him and you; ordering withal your co-habitation under the noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Husband and Wife. But (ſuppoſing <hi>Placi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> be yet alive) our union will meet with great oppoſition from <hi>Fadrique</hi>'s inſolent Nephews. Nay, <hi>Madam</hi> (ſaid he) leave that to me: for I am wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to loſe the reputation of a Gentleman, yea, and life it ſelf, if I do not carry on the matter ſo wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily, that in great peace, without the leaſt ſhadow of fear or danger, you ſhall enjoy <hi>Placidus</hi> for your loving Husband. Thus <hi>Agnes</hi> went to her Cloſet with great Joy. <hi>Placidus</hi> could not eaſily be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded of the poſſibility of the matter; yet hi
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:61065:23"/>companions pregnant wit and knowledge, added ſome confidence to him, for <hi>Viteli</hi> had undertaken, not only to remove <hi>Fadrique</hi>'s preſent Diſtemper, but alſo to renew his Youth and ſtrength, chiefly that by ſuch means (a ſophiſm indeed) <hi>Placidus</hi> might attain to the enjoyment of his longed for <hi>Agnes:</hi> For which cauſe (ſaid the ingenious <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iteli</hi> in the preſence of learned Phyſitians) you ſhall in a very ſhort time perceive, <hi>Fadrique</hi> brisk and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gorous, with Teeth, Hair, and Colour ſutable to the age of thirty or forty years. Thoſe learned men laughed him to ſcorn; and the Lady doubted of the matter greatly. But to put an end to doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and mocking, he ſpake to the Phyſitians in the preſence of <hi>Agnes, Charles</hi> and <hi>Bernard</hi> after this manner:</p>
               <p>I muſt confeſs the oppoſition of ſuch Judicious men might terrifie <hi>Galen, Hyppocrates,</hi> and <hi>Eſcula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pius,</hi> of whom it's reported, That he raiſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf from the Dead. How much then may a Novice (ſuch as I am) tremble when I conſider that I have undertaken in your preſence to demonſtrate, how the radical moiſture may be reſtored; inſomuch that decrepit old Age ſhall be conſtrained to Cloath it ſelf with the Colour, Vigour, and other quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of brisk Youth: Nevertheleſs, the ſtrength which attends truth reduced to practice, revives my fainting Spirits; ſo that with confidence I affirm the certainty (as well as the poſſibility) of my demonſtration, which I ſhall endeavour to evince in the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Tongue (though with the greater dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulty) for the ſatisfaction of <hi>Agnes, Charles</hi> and <hi>Bernard,</hi> the Parties moſtly concerned.</p>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:61065:24"/>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Gentlemen,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>You know very well, Experience, Authority and Reaſon, are the ſureſt foundations by which any truth can be ſupported; From all which my Propoſition ſhall be made evident.</p>
                     <p>The Learned <hi>Arnaldus, Villa Nova, Tully, Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>celſus, Cardanus,</hi> and others, whom we need not mention, favour us in this point; as alſo the Alchy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts <hi>Arbor vitae:</hi> ſo that Authorities abound with us.</p>
                     <p>In the next place, <hi>Blaicus de Taranto</hi> affirms that in <hi>Saguntum</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Valentia,</hi> there was a Nunn of ſixty years, whoſe age was renewed, having Teeth, Hair, Colour and Vigour, as if ſhe had been but thirty years old.</p>
                     <p>And <hi>Antonius Torquemada</hi> in his Dialogues, gives us an account of an Old Man who was reſtored to ſtrength, being one hundred years old; after which wonderful change he lived fifty years. From which Author and common Tradition, we hear of ſuch an inſtance in <hi>Toledo.</hi> All learned men know that paſſage related by <hi>Ferdinandus de Caſtaneda,</hi> lib. 8. And by <hi>Petrus Malfeus,</hi> lib. 3. Hiſt. Ind. how that a Noble Man of <hi>India</hi> lived Three hundred and forty years, in which time his Age was renewed thrice.</p>
                     <p>If we conſult reaſon, we ſhall find her no leſs fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable than Authority or experience: For what
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:61065:24"/>is Youth, but an equality or proportion of natural heat and radical moiſture? Yea, according to <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len</hi> and all other learned Phyſitians, the difference of the Ages is deduced from the different operati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the natural heat. And <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> affirms, that the nature of Old Age conſiſts in Frigidity and Sic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>city; from whoſe Explication, <hi>Lib. de Long. &amp; brev. vitae</hi> we learn, that ſuch men wax old ſooneſt, whoſe Life has been attended with greateſt labours and cares, which cauſe a <hi>diſpendium</hi> of the natural heat. Therefore (if this be true) it ſeems that Humid Medicaments, with hot Potions and Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations may reſtore decaying Age, by reducing the radical moiſture, and natural heat to ſuch a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion as they enjoy in Youth. And it is obſerved, that the Divine Providence has furniſhed divers Stones, Herbs and Waters with qualities, which, (if known) would ſilence all cavillings in this matter. It is reported by <hi>Cardanus, Langius,</hi> and <hi>Petrus Chieza</hi> that in <hi>Bonica</hi> and <hi>Lucaya</hi> Wells are extant whoſe Waters are more delicious than the choiceſt Wines, having in them vertue to renew a mans Age; this is teſtified by <hi>Ariſ. lib</hi> 3. <hi>Hiſt. Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal. Cap.</hi> 12. and other Authors of good note. <hi>Homer</hi> alſo mentioneth the like of Herbs. And me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks although the Simples requiſite for producing ſuch ſtrange effects be not commonly known, yet it's <hi>a male Sequitur</hi> to infer, therefore no man knows them: Yea, no man in ſober reaſon can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, that Spirits are contained in Herbs, Waters and Stones; which being once granted, it neceſſarily follows that theſe, when well extracted and applied, may ſerve to carry on ſuch a rare work, as I now
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:61065:25"/>mention, and am about to demonſtrate. Further, it's obſervable that I have been travelling many years, by which I had occaſion to diſcourſe with <hi>Mahomet</hi>'s Phyſitians, as alſo with <hi>Arabians, Perſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Phenicians;</hi> upon which conſideration it may be ſuſpected that I know things not diſcovered as yet in this place: Wherefore, I ſhall, (with God's Grace) reſtore <hi>Fadrique</hi> to ſtrength and health, ſeeing I perfectly underſtand his malady and Complexion. But you may ask, if in ſuch a caſe he may be called young? I anſwer, not at all; but that he is in a better diſpoſition for life according to his nature. Now if this Theory ſuffice not to ſtop the Mouths of Wranglers; the matter ſhall be put beyond all doubt by practice. Thus ended <hi>Viteli</hi> his pertinent Diſcourſe. Who (after the dying Old Man had been committed to him) made a <hi>paction,</hi> that none ſhould diſturb him by coming into the room where he was to tarry with the ſick Perſon, except ſuch as he called; and that Apothecaries ſhould grant him what Simples he pleaſed to ask; all perſons conſented to thoſe demands: but none more cordially and chearfully than <hi>Agnes,</hi> who was privy to <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iteli</hi>'s deſign. The next day was appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the work. <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iteli</hi> having repaired to his Lodging, diſcovered to <hi>Placidus</hi> how much he was applauded by the Phyſitians; and alſo that <hi>Agnes</hi> was exceeding glad, the young men <hi>Charles</hi> and <hi>Bernard</hi> being much dejected: and he perſiſted in the former confidence that all things would ſucceed aright, and be brought to an happy iſſue. He ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly charged <hi>Placidus</hi> to eſchew all Society, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that the Non-obſervance of that Rule, had a
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:61065:25"/>neceſſary tendency to marr the curious contrivance. Then he returned to the Patient, to whom he gave a portion, which being mingled with a little Poyſon, ſet the Old Man's Tongue at work, giving vigour and Agility to his body in a ſhort time, to the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration of all Beholders.</p>
                     <p>After which <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iteli</hi> ſpake privately to <hi>Agnes,</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Madam, <hi>Fadrique</hi> will not in all probability live nine daies: therefore it's convenient to call <hi>Placidus,</hi> ſeeing the Old Man in his laſt Will has made you his heir, appointing a thouſand pounds for each of his Nephews, to either of which if you be married, the Poſſeſſions ſet apart for you are loſt. But, if you chooſe <hi>Placidus</hi> for your Husband, he muſt in all reaſon receive the half of his Fathers ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance. Now you ſee how nearly you are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerned to hearken to my Propoſitions, ſeeing mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters ſhall be ſo dextrouſly carried on, that all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons will conclude <hi>Fadrique</hi> yet alive. This I hope will prove acceptable and comfortable to you and <hi>Placidus,</hi> whom I ought to ſerve according to my capacity while I live.</p>
                     <p>The Old Man, will go down to the Grave with Joy, by this courſe, which will create affliction to his inſolent Nephews. Not long after <hi>Fadrique</hi> dyeth, and is buried after a moſt clandeſtine man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner; in whoſe place they ſubſtitute <hi>Placidus,</hi> whom all perſons affirmed to have been <hi>Fadrique</hi> reſtored to Health and Vigour. Which buſineſs being fully concluded to the ſatisfaction of the Parties moſtly concerned; <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iteli</hi> proſecuted his deſign of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velling.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:61065:26"/>This Relation diſcovers much of the Worlds Deceitfulneſs, which is frequently defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by great Authorities improved with diſinge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuity.</p>
                     <p>Sir, I ſhall add no more concerning the Solemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty at <hi>Madrid,</hi> and the Hiſtory of <hi>Placidus,</hi> wiſhing that your pleaſure in reading may correſpond to the deſire I entertained to ſatisfie your curioſity in writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſame.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <salute>Farewel.</salute>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:61065:26"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
